Guide to the Veljko Bulajić Collection
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Veljko Bulajić collection
1914-1977
MS 1689
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
0.75
(2 boxes)
The collection consists of transcripts of interviews conducted by Veljko Bulajić, a Yugoslav filmmaker, in preparation for a television biography of Josip Broz Tito. There are also a few transcripts for interviews conducted by others. The collection also contains copies of photographs from various repositories of Tito or important people, places, and events in his life.
Bulajić, Veljko
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferfed from the Slavic Collection, 1995.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Arrangement
Arranged in two series: I. Interview Transcripts, 1953, 1970, 1973-1977. II. Photographs, ca. 1914-1967.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of transcripts of interviews conducted by Veljko Bulajić, a Yugoslav filmmaker, in preparation for a television biography of Josip Broz Tito. There are also a few transcripts for interviews conducted by others. The collection also contains copies of photographs from various repositories of Tito or important people, places, and events in his life.
Heads of state -- Yugoslavia -- Interviews; Yugoslavia -- Foreign relations -- 1945-1980; Yugoslavia -- History -- 1918-1945; Yugoslavia -- History -- 1945-1980; Yugoslavia -- Politics and government -- 1945-1980; Bulajić, Veljko; Tito, Josip Broz, 1892-1980
- Interview Transcripts, 1953, 1970, 1973-1977; Series I
  Scope and Contents
  This series consists primarily of carbon copies of transcripts of interviews that Veljko Bulajić conducted with Josip Broz Tito and his colleagues. Many of the transcripts contain handwritten annotations and editing. While Bulajić conducted most of the interviews, there are also a few from other sources, apparently collected by him. There is also one published statement included (by Krsto Popivoda). All of the transcripts are in Croatian.
  - Augustinčić́, Antun (10 pages), 1973 October 18 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Bakarić́, Vladimir (60 pages), 1974 April 8, 15, October 22 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Bandaranaike, Sirimavo (5 pages), [translated from English], undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Beloglavek, Ivan (2 pages), 1977 September (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Broz, Stjepan (3 pages), 1974 March 15 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Čolaković́, Rodoljub (56 pages - pg. 15 missing), 1974 January 17 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Dapčević, Peko (11 pages), 1974 January 10 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Galogaža, Hermina (5 pages), [interviewer: Ljubo (Šikić?), includes statement by Mate Matok], 1976 December (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Gobac, Antun (7 pages), 1974 March 21 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Ibarruri, Dolores (4 pages), [translated from Spanish], 1977 September (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Jakac, Božidar (17 pages), 1974 March 15, 19 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Janković, General Mića, (43 pages), undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Kardelja, Edvard (64 pages), 1977 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Kornejev, General (10 pages), [translated from Russian], undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Krajačić, Beba (7 pages), 1973 October 10 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Krajačić-Stevo, Ivan (35 pages), undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Krajger, Sergej (15 pages), [interview in Slovenian with Croatian translation], 1977 September (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - MacLean, Fitzroy, (8 pages), [translation from English], undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Marokini, Dr. Ivan (15 pages), 1974 February 22 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Mihajlović (Soviet pilot) (7 pages), [translated from Russian], 1977 September (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Norodom Sihanuk, H.R.H. (3 pages), [translated from French; includes statement of Stjepan Jovelić], 1977 September (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Orović, Savo (6 pages), [includes 2 page description of photographs and interview with Filip Pavešić, 1974 Feb 21 (2 pages)], 1974 February 19 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Pavešić, Filip (6 pages), 1974 March 21 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Petrović, Nikola (26 pages), 1974 February 23 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Popivoda, Krsto (8 pages), 1976 December (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Published statement concerning his behavior with the police and in court, 1970. (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Rajter, Jaša (24 pages), [interviewer: Ljubo (Šikić?); also includes statement of Krsto Popivoda (6 pages)], 1973 October 11, 1977 March 10 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Smirnov, Vladimir (12 pages), [interviewer: Šikić. Translated into Serbian from Russian. Includes "Tito's Memoirs" Marko Špogarić (1 page)], 1974 January 30 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Stipetić, Milutin (4 pages), [handwritten with hand-drawn map], 1975 April 4 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Sudec, Marshal (17 pages), [translated from Russian], undated (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Taušan, Vida (3 pages), 1973 October 22 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Tito, Josip Broz (14 pages), [Interviewer: Slava Ogrizović], 1953 May 7 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - (107 pages), undated (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Velebit, Vladko (22 pages), undated (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Vraneš, Mihajlo (1 page), undated (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Vukmanović-Tempo, Svetozar (8 pages), 1973 October 22 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Žugić, Tomo (3 pages), [interviewer: Ljubo (Šikić?)], 1973 October 26 (Box 1, Folder 37)
- Photographs, circa 1914-1967; Series II
  This series contains photographs related to Josip Broz Tito assembled by Veljko Bulajić. The photographs appear to be copies of images from various repositories; there are no original images. While many of the images are of Tito, a significant portion are of people, places, and events important in his career but in which he does not appear.
  - Family photographs, undated (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Tito at his desk and at unidentified event, undated (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Tito's identification documents (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Pester, Lloyd, "The Fencing Tournament", 1914 May 29 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Serbia and the Balkans during World War I, 1914-1918 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Inter-war period [includes Lenin speaking at an international rally in St. Petersburg (1920 Jul 19), members of the Yugoslav RKP(b) in Moscow (1921 Apr 10), and a group of Russian Civil War participants from Yugoslavia in Riga, 1921] (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Communist Party activities, 1924, 1928-1929 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Trade union activities [copies of documents and one photograph], 1928 (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Photographs and documents concerning the trial of Tito in Zagreb, 1928 (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Tito in Lepoglava Prison, 1928-1933(?) (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Sino-Japanese War, 1932 (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - CPJ Conference in Žabljak, 1940, 1941 (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - World War II
    - Belgrade, 1941 (Box 2, Folder 50)
    - Tito and partisans, 1941, 1943-1944 (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - "Who is Tito?" Neue Ordung, February 28 (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - Signing of the proclamation of the SFR Yugoslavia, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - Tito in the Soviet Union
    - 1945 (Box 2, Folder 54)
    - 1956 Jun (Box 2, Folder 55)
    - 1962 Dec (Box 2, Folder 56)
    - 1967 Nov (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - Tito and the Executive Committee of the CC CPJ, Ljubljana, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 58)
  - First Conference of the Non-Aligned Movement, Belgrade, 1960(?) (Box 2, Folder 59)
  - Tito at the General Assembly of the UN, undated (Box 2, Folder 60)
  - Tito and Leonid Brezhnev, Belgrade(?), undated (Box 2, Folder 61)
  - Tito and Dolores Ibarruri, undated (Box 2, Folder 62)
  - Buildings in Zagreb and other cities(?), undated (Box 2, Folder 63)
  - Photographs of Palmiro Togliatti, Vladko Maček, Pentkenukjehev, and D.Z. Manuilski, undated (Box 2, Folder 64)